[Music]
hello people hello everybody episode 125
of azkabajit is live on the air i hope
you're doing very well
today we discuss geopolitics current
affairs history etc but before we do
that as always let me
see who all is there
i can see bhaskar software's creative
[Music]
and lots of other people
the rim jim
and everybody else good evening good day
to all of you wherever you are
all right let us take some questions
shall we as always we have
lots of questions
so today let's start with a question
about history instead of geopolitics for
a change
okay
prabhanjan says what was the very first
war in the whole of the world that is
recorded
and documented in history where did it
happen and between whom
interesting question which was the very
first war that has ever been recorded
let us go to the map as always
and see where this war happened
where is
our map here it is on the screen now
here we are
here's the map
and the very first war that is recorded
happened
in this region
somewhere around here in the sindhu
region
the first war that has ever been
recorded in history in literature
is the war or rather the battle so to
say of the ten kings the dash
that happened god knows when a very very
long time ago it is recorded in i think
mandel seven of the rigveda
and there are several verses that uh
reference this
this battle that happened okay so where
did this battle this war or this battle
happen it it happened on the banks of
the purushini river
the purushri river is now called the
ravi river it's most likely the ravi
river okay
so who were the people that participated
in this battle that's the question
so on the one hand you had uh sudas
king sudas was the grandson of uh king
devodas
he he belonged to the bharat clan
of ancient india
right so his people they resided they
lived on the eastern bank of this river
the parochial river the ravi river of of
today
so the ravi river mostly goes through
pakistan present day pakistan
temporarily yes
and it passes through the city of lahore
lavapoor
and it originates somewhere in the
himalayan foothills in in
the himachal pradesh region
so the bharat clan of ancient india
resided they lived on the eastern bank
of the ravi river and when this
entire event happened their king was
king sudas
now what was happening is that on the
western bank of the ravi river there
were all these different uh there were
other clans that used to live beyond the
the west right beyond the beyond the
ravi river to the west so which were
these clans they were the anus the
who are the
well the the ancestors of the persians
then you had the pakta clan
ancestors of the pakhtuns
you had the prithu clan the ancestors of
the parthians you had other clans like
the alina the brigu clan and many other
clans all right
so all of these people these people
these clans that lived to the west of
the ravi river they were
they uh they used to raid
on the eastern side they used to try and
steal cattle from the bharatapi from the
bharat clan and they had this very
antagonistic relationship with the
bharatas right
so eventually this all came to a head
and uh
so king's with us
the king of the birth clan
he had to
fight
a battle
against an entire coalition of these
western clans
so these western clans the parshu the
pakta the anus the alinas the brigos and
so on so forth they were also
indians
but they lived to the west of the ravi
so the battle happened on the banks of
the ravi river yeah the the parshuni
river
and
the bharatas were able to prevail
king sudas
won
the battle he won the war and all of
these clans they had to run for their
lives
they essentially were exiled out of
india they were expelled out of india
they used to come from the northwest
they had to get out of
india and go into central asia
so some clients went into central asia
which was uh uttara madra
yes
and uh some clans like the like the
parshu clan the parsha
they went westwards through balochistan
and they eventually ended up in iran
and they gave their name to iran the
parshwa clan gave the name then the
country became persia it
came to be called as persia right
so sudhas you can say king sudas
he can be considered to be the first
recorded war hero in history the first
victorious king in any recorded war or
battle kings with
and because it was the bharat clan that
won
this war this battle
that's why
india is called bharath today right so
we are the descendants of the bharatas
of the bharat clan
all of us whoever is watching if you are
of indian origin
you will have a certain percentage of
your ancestry that comes from the
bharata from from the bharata people who
lived in india at that time there is a
guarantee
right
so that is
the first of war that has ever been
recorded it is recorded in the most
ancient
text that is known to humankind which is
the rigveda the rigveda is the oldest
literature in the history of humanity
and in the rig veda we have the record
of this
very ancient
battle or war so it is called the battle
of the ten kings but against so on the
one hand you had the bharatas
led by king sudas on the other hand on
the other side you had a coalition a
confederation of more than ten clans
it's called the battle of the ten kings
but there were more than ten clans that
were arrayed against king bharat so he
faced great odds and he surmounted those
odds he's the first victorious king that
we know of in human history he's the
first war hero that we know of in human
history
king sudas grandson of king devadasa so
that is in brief a very brief overview
of the battle of the ten kings the first
war in recorded history
she says attempt number 782
see
i see lots of people writing down what
attempt it is how many times they're
trying to ask the question listen
if you're trying to guilt me into into
picking your questions it's not really
going to work i pick questions that are
interesting that have not been asked
before and that are relevant
so you can go on this question even
though there's an attempt listed over it
it's an interesting question that's all
picked it i've not picked it because it
is attempt number four or attempt number
whatever i've picked it because it's
interesting so if you want me to pick
your questions please ask interesting
questions good questions that will be
relevant to everybody to all to the
entire audience to a wider audience
okay with that said the question is this
what does the deal of haifa port mean
for india
what is its strategic importance and
considering the fact that gautam adani a
private businessman has bought the port
to what extent will the central
government of india be able to interfere
all right
where is haifa haifa is the largest
port in israel so let us once again
bring out the map
here's the map
so where is israel israelis is not the
eastern uh
banks of the mediterranean sea south of
lebanon west of jordan
north of
misra egypt
so haifa
so this is what israel looks like it's
not a very large place and there are
certain interesting places in israel let
me just take a small detour before we go
to haifa
so there is this place called beer shiva
very ancient place close to beersheba
you have this
town called deemona
and near the mona you have an
interesting um
interesting installation
that you may be able to recognize what
the shape looks like you see this so i'm
not revealing any great secrets it's all
available in the public domain but yeah
interesting places in israel
anyhow let's go back to the port of
haifa where is it it's further to the
north of yerushalayim north of tel aviv
here is haifa port
so this is the port that we are
discussing let's go to satellite imagery
uh
it is israel's largest port the most
significant port and uh
it's a very it's it's a nice natural
harbor it's got these break waters and
lots of terminals etc
and there is an airport right next to it
i'm sure there's a train station etc all
that nearby very well connected port and
uh yeah
so this is the port that we are
discussing this is the port that has
been acquired by the adani group now uh
it says over here the question is that
mr adani has bought the port that is not
quite the case he has not bought the
port the port has been acquired on lees
until the year 2050 something 2054 2055
right and
the adani group has acquired a 70
share
in the port and there's an israeli
group
i think it is called the gadot group i
believe
that has acquired the remaining 30
percent so it's a it's a collaboration
kind of thing
but the adani group has a controlling uh
stake in this deal it's on lease until
the 2050s right
so this is what the port is and it's
interesting that the the this deal
happened
right after the uh i2u2 summit between
india
the united states israel and the uae so
the u.s president mr byron had gone to
israel he had visited by israel and
that's
it and while he was there this summit
happened this discussion between the
four leaders of these countries and
right almost right after this this uh
i2u2 summit this deal was announced
right
so uh
so this is a private company the adani
group is a private company and and what
is the significance of this deal the
significance of this deal is that it
brings india and israel closer together
right india and israel already have a
close relationship and it brings india
and israel further closer together
um
this is not actually
something that the americans are trying
to engineer some people are saying that
this is the beginnings of a of a middle
eastern quad the i2u2 has been ported as
a middle eastern quad and maybe they are
saying that this is part of it and it's
becoming a strategic thing uh it may not
quite be the same i don't think this has
been engineered by the the americans but
here's the deal see the uh the adani
group
is already connected it's already
participating in the defense sector
with israeli different defense firms
it is in the process of setting up a
drone manufacturing company in india
it's in the process of doing it or maybe
it has already done it and it is doing
it in collaboration it partner in
partnership with israeli defense firms
so
now that the adani group is uh involved
in this matter as well it uh
it makes the relationship stronger
and
it will offer israeli companies a better
foothold into india because this
partnership is now stronger and it is
more like a strategic partnership right
um the other thing is that the the
india
has a very good relationship with the
various gcc states the gulf cooperation
council states
and israel has a good relationship
between with the uae and with bahrain so
this will help israel get get closer and
have better relations with the gcc
states so that is something that will
benefit israel and this is obviously of
course a
an alternative to the chinese uh
maritime silk road
so the chinese are
trying to create this maritime silk road
and they want to control the uh
the trading routes
the the infrastructure and all that yeah
the supply chains and all that so this
is going to be a viable alternative to
that it will offer india a foothold in
the mediterranean it will offer india a
way to get into uh the middle east and
the further west into the mediterranean
region into into europe and all that
yeah so we are seeing this new thing
happening it's an alternative to what
the chinese are doing and even what the
chinese are doing with iran and russia
the international north south transit
corridor which they are trying to set up
yeah so we are seeing the emergence of a
parallel infrastructure now
and this is a major step in that
direction the chinese there is a chinese
company that also has a
that also
uh operates a terminal somewhere in
haifa not in this port but nearby so the
chinese will not be happy about this i
believe the chinese were trying to
uh acquire
uh what the adani group has acquired
they were trying to acquire lease
long-term lease in the haifa port but
obviously that would not work out
because the americans would not be happy
and maybe the israelis don't also want
to get too close to china
if there is a chinese presence it's
always problematic there's various
angles to it geopolitical angle spying
angle and all that
right so what we are seeing is that this
is this is something that is purely
between india and israel i do not think
personally that the americans have any
hand in engineering this
so we are witnessing
parallel supply chains parallel transit
trade corridors etc being created uh
an india
arab mediterranean trade corridor kind
of thing
via israel and the ua may most likely be
involved in this and other nations of
the gcc club may also get involved so we
are witnessing multi-polarity
the americans want bipolarity the
chinese want unipolarity it's nations
like india israel france even russia
which is not part of this but these
nations want multi-polarity and this is
what we are witnessing so we are
witnessing right now the beginning of
this sort of cooperation uh bilateral
cooperation between india and israel
trilateral trilateral cooperation
between india israel uae most likely the
uae will also be part of this supply
this this corridor trade corridor and uh
so that's what's happening we are seeing
a changing of the geopolitical balance
for the longest time india was not
involved anywhere now the question is
that adani group is a private company
yes
so will the
government of india be able to interfere
there is no question of interference
see
today a lot of geopolitics is played
by private companies and obviously when
you have a private company of a certain
nation that gets involved in something
like this that nation is automatically
involved and
so that's how it is so the private
companies often act as proxies of the
government in a variety of ways and we
know that the gauta madani group is very
close
well that's what the media says it's
very close to the government of india
the current uh government of india so
that is something that works in india's
favor right
and mr adani i think he had made he had
said this that this is not it's not
about the money it's uh it's a strategic
move that the adani group is making
and
so this is a win-win for the adanis it
is a win-win for india israel even the
uae so it is a positive step
all together
looking at it from all
all possible angles and this is going to
uh definitely lead to a strengthening of
the india israel
relationship cooperation the strategic
relationship and we could see more such
things happening in the future you will
have more israeli investment in india
you'll have more collaboration between
india indian companies and israeli
companies
from in the defense sector in other
sectors as well trade sector etc it's
good so overall that's what's happening
uh
it's it's a
30 plus year lease i think it's until
night it's until 2055 or 2054. so it's a
long-term uh game that has been played
here and it's good for india as well as
as well as israel
next
tech curiosity says please tell us about
the us military's project
100 000 or mcnamara's morons in the
vietnam war
so the vietnam war is a conflict that
started in the 1950s
it went on until until the 1970s the
americans eventually finally withdrew
from vietnam
in if i'm not mistaken in 1973
somewhere around there you can refer the
dates and find the exact dates and they
got involved militarily with troops on
the ground with boats on the ground
properly in the 1960s was it 62 was it
63 look it up if you're interested right
so
so then this war uh began in
in earnest there were lots of american
troops that were needed on vietnamese
soil in order to defeat the communists
that were supported by various
other nations yeah
so
what the americans
had to face
is they had to start a recruitment drive
they had to draft people
they had to ask for people to
voluntarily join the armed forces and
there was opposition there was
resistance to this it was a 1960s people
were into into flower power people were
into the hippie lifestyle people were
into love and peace and all that and
they did not like this
this project that the americans the
american government had started of
interfering in in the foreign nation it
was all started by the very pacifistic
president uh mr kennedy right it's it's
surprising that well it's not really
surprising but that's how it works
so it all began with with president
kennedy kennedy's actions and then he
was assassinated obviously
63 i believe and lyndon johnson became
the president he was vice president then
because kennedy was assassinated lyndon
johnson became the president and robert
mcnamara was the defense secretary of
the u.s he served under president
kennedy and then under president johnson
so around this time there was a great
need for u.s soldiers to to to to pull
american civilians into the military and
obviously when you enter the military
there are certain tests that you have to
go through there is a certain aptitude
test a mental affective test fitness
test do you do you uh are you good
enough to be in the army right you'll be
tested
so uh
this project hundred thousand was an
experiment of sorts
in this project in this experiment they
lowered the standards
of of the intake right so there would be
a mental test uh an intelligence test or
there's something like that right mental
attitude test so
uh they lowered the standards for that
and even for the physical uh
requirements they lowered the standards
so what happened is that a bunch of
people
more than 200 000 more than 2 lakhs
about 230 or 250 000
soldiers were
part of this experiment
and they did not really fulfill
the standards that the american army had
many of them could not
many of them were illiterate
many of them could not speak english
some of them were overweight some of
them were underweight
and there was a control group of regular
people who could actually uh
pass the past the tests and fulfill the
requirements so about 230 000 or 250 000
such soldiers were drafted into the army
and they were called mcnamara's misfits
or mcnamara's morons and some other
other terms were also used
and they the american army and the
bureaucracy they kept track of the
performance of these people right and
what was discovered is that the
performance was bad
they were way more likely to get killed
in combat they were way more likely to
get arrested
by their own military police for various
infractions and transgressions etc
uh so they did very poorly yeah it was
not a very very successful experiment at
that time what was also happening was
that there was this uh
the the war against poverty or something
that lyndon johnson was was it was a new
campaign he had started a political
thing right back home
uh war against poverty or fight against
poverty or something
and robert mcnamara
tried to construe
or interpret or portray this experiment
as part of the war against poverty so
essentially he was saying that we are
trying to use the american armed forces
as an employment generation scheme
by lowering the standards slightly it
was more than slightly
so these people
who were part of this experiment they
did poorly in the armed forces
they were way more likely to get killed
percentage-wise then the normal soldiers
they were way more likely to get
arrested and have the problems after
they were discharged after the war was
over
uh
their unemployment rates were much
higher their alcoholism rates were much
higher their divorce rates were much
higher so even after they were released
back into the civilian population they
fared very poorly they were much more
susceptible to ptsd post-traumatic
stress disorder because they did not
have the mental attitude to to withstand
battle and you know to deal with it the
way a regular soldier would
yeah
so the americans did this strange
experiment they they lowered the
standards of their military for this and
the results were not good the results
were quite bad
so that is what this thing is and if you
watch the movie forest forest gump
it's about a soul an american citizen
who is not very bright
yeah and he is drafted into the army and
he serves in the vietnam war
uh it doesn't explicitly state that he
was part of the mcnamara's morons
experiment but there is no other way
that a person like forrest gump with the
less than average less than standard
uh iq and intelligence and aptitude in
anything would have been part of the
army and would have been dropped into
the army and would have been allowed to
take part part in the vietnam war
so uh
this is a failed experiment they tried
to use the military the american
military as an employment generation
scheme please understand my dear friends
the military is not an employment
generation scheme the military does not
exist to give you employment
the military
let's talk about the indian military
there's a movie right now that's a
complete copy of forrest gump in which
they they portray a person who seems to
be borderline that's how he has
been acted right that's how the
portrayal is
and that person is in the indian army
the indian army has high standards
the indian army has very high standards
fitness standards
mental aptitude standards and all that
so the port rail is terrible the indian
army would never ever allow
this sort of experiment to happen in
india
and also remember that the armed forces
are not an employment generation scheme
since we are talking about this let me
let me let me let me reiterate that
the armed forces do not exist to give
you all employment the armed forces have
only one purpose
to deal with national security
right so so that's what it is about so
the americans tried to do this
experiment in which they used the armed
forces as an employment generation
scheme part of the
part of the us president's war against
poverty and it misfired very badly and
those people they had very bad lives
afterwards even after they were
discharged so that in brief
is about the american military's project
hundred thousand also known as
mcnamara's misfits or mcnamara's morons
that's what they called it
okay a couple of questions mayank says
hello sir what if india two were to
frame a one india policy will our
so-called strategic alliance allied
partners accept it
and dave says jahin sir jayhindev
uh when will india's foreign policy be
aggressive and follow chanaky for china
and when will the government of india
support the independence of tibet and
take big take back
pakistan occupied jaman kashmir and
aksai chin
okay
think about it this way
let's say i have a pet
pet cat
so my pet cat
decides
that from tomorrow
i'm going to behave like a tiger
yeah
my my policy i'm going to change my
policies from tomorrow morning onwards
and i'm going to have the same policy
that the tiger has
will my pet cat be able
to overnight become a tiger and be
feared and be
be just like a dagger i don't think so
right
let's say i have
a dog
and my dog decides that from tomorrow
morning i will adopt the policies that a
bear
has
will that dog get the same results let's
say i have a goldfish in in a bowl and
my goldfish says tomorrow morning
onwards i'm going to behave like a shark
will that goldfish get the same results
so
what i'm trying to say is that
you may change your policies but your
policies must reflect your actual
capabilities
they must reflect the ground realities
they cannot be
part of some imaginary universe that you
may think you live in
right so when when we are saying that
let's
frame a one india policy so the chinese
have one china policy and most nations
abide by it
today india i think today india said
that we don't explicitly abide by the
one china policy which is a good
statement but china has this policy it's
able to enforce it mostly because other
nations fear china with good reason the
chinese are a very massive economy and
they have a very massive military so
other nations have reason to fear the
chinese and nations that are far away
wish to benefit from chinese from
china's economic cooperation that's why
they abide by the one china policy the
americans are not doing that
now if india were to claim that we have
a one india policy we would like that to
happen but are we powerful enough for
that to be enforced for us to be able to
enforce that right now we are not that
powerful please understand that
right now when we talk about uh
supporting the independence of tibet and
taking back poke and accession
it has to be within the realms of
india's capabilities today today india
is not in a position to initiate a war
with the chinese and grab territory and
grab back the territory that they have
stolen from us as of today there is an
asymmetry of power the chinese if they
start a war with india they will be they
will they will regret it because there
are certain alliance that in india will
not allow the chinese to cross we have
those capabilities but we do not have
the capabilities of today
to go and take back tibet or liberate
tibet we don't have that as of today
right
so
we can try and
be aggressive with our words and all but
what point does it does it serve
right so chanakiniti is not about being
aggressive
chanakyani is about being patient
and and and doing what is the right
thing
for the long-term benefit
china kennedy is not about being angry
and being aggressive and all that china
kenneth is all kinds of things it's also
about pretending to be weak and biding
your time
so please understand what chanakiniti
actually is please actually read the
book if you can
right so india will
frame will india will declare a one
india policy when it is strong enough
to have it enforced by everybody else
as of today if we say we have a one
india policy then the chinese will
explicitly go and do something about it
and they have been issued in the past
they issued visas with with the wrong
map the child and and
and the pakistanis they hold our
territory so
the chinese only when we regain the
territories in due time can we enforce
such a policy so it's about patience
india is not there yet please understand
this we are not there yet
we have to be realistic
look around see the actual situation of
the world
we cannot
it's like it's like a cat saying i'm
from tomorrow i'm a tiger that's not how
it works i'm not trying to compare india
with a cat i'm just giving an analogy
right india is a great nation but we are
still not powerful enough we will be in
the future
the time will come be patient and work
towards that all of us need to work
towards it in our own
individual
ways channa kennedy may already be
being in progress
and it's not supposed to be visible to
everybody
right so that's how it is
okay another similar question uh titan
says when no why do our success why are
our successive governments silent when
it comes to tackling china at the border
our leaders and media generally don't
comment on chinese action on the border
be it intrusion constructions of
structures and land occupation
so the question is why is our government
silent
so the alternative is not being silent
and making statements
and what what goes good does that serve
making strong statements you know what
they call it in hindi kari linda
means a
strong
harsh condemnation with strong words
what does it do
words are words words are immaterial how
many times do i have to keep repeating
this
actions matter and you don't publicize
your actions ever
you keep it quiet
there are all these
various very prominent individuals that
that
i'm not naming anybody but there are
lots of these very prominent people some
of them who say that who who have the
same criticism that the government is
weak need it doesn't make any strong
statements and all statements do nothing
words are just words
it's actions that matter
right so we don't know what's happening
the media will portray all kinds of
things they don't really they don't
really have access to the border regions
we have satellite imagery we have ocean
and all that so we have some idea of
what's happening
and it's being construed and spun in
various ways and all that
see it's very simple
you should be quiet
your actions should speak larger louder
than your words
making strong statements and condemning
what the chinese are doing or may not be
doing or whatever it what difference
does it make on the real world
it's like you know you have two boxers
whoever fight in a week's time and one
of them is very aggressive and makes
huge statements and i'm gonna beat him
up i'm gonna knock him out in the first
round i'm gonna do this i'm gonna do
that and when the fight happens you know
what happens
so there's no point being aggressive
verbally and and uh not being silent
silence
or the lack of it is immaterial only
actions matter
right and the actions will be taken or
may already be be in progress we may not
know about it it all depends on our
capabilities it all depends on how
strong we are as a nation overall what
is our comprehensive national power like
that's a measure of your overall
strength it it takes into account your
gdp the
what kind of materials you are producing
how much of what your export import uh
balance is like
uh
what sort of military you do you have
what sort of diplomatic relations you
have and a variety of factors your
comprehensive national power
that is what determines how strong
you are and how you can tackle other
nations
words are immaterial words are pointless
i don't listen to people's words
i keep saying this
if you want to truly understand what a
leader is like ignore his or her words
completely
only see their actions look at their
track record over the past 10 20 30
years
that is what will tell you what the real
value is what the real worth is
okay so words don't matter people can
speak a lot but that that is pointless
all right
srihari arjun says china has docked its
spy vessel in sri lanka and india did
not take any action why did india face
this diplomatic diplomatic defeat
despite giving aid to sri lanka and
being much closer to it than china in
terms of distance
i'm not sure if the vessel has docked
there yet but it i think the sri lankans
have now
given the chinese vessel permission to
dock from the 16th to the to the 21 21st
or 22nd of this month
uh august 2022
so yes
that
is something that is
well it goes against india's interest
against india's national interest
and that is something that the sri
lankans need to uh face some
consequences for i am not talking about
the sri lankan public
i'm not talking about the people of sri
lanka we have absolutely nothing against
the people of sri lanka they are they
are our own people
yeah the sri lankan government which is
in power right now
which has come to power recently after
the
hasty exit of the rajapaksa
dynasty so this new government under mr
ranil vikram singh who is a western
stooge yeah this government has allowed
has given permission to china to to
to to allow this vessel to dock in
hambantota port
so this obviously is
you
i think we can constru we can consider
this to be a hostile action against
india
yeah so
why did we face this diplomatic defeat
because the sri lankans are not scared
enough of india as of today
it's very simple diplomacy is war by
other means understand this diplomacy is
not nice words and nice meetings and all
that diplomacy is about holding a club a
stick behind your back and talking nice
that is what diplomacy is and how
effective your diplomacy is depends
solely on how big the stick is that
you're holding behind your back so the
sri lankans have done this because they
are not scared enough of india
they
are pretty certain
mr vikrama singh and his minions whoever
it is they are pretty certain that they
are quite safe
and they will face no real world
consequences for this behavior from
india
that is why they have done this
is this a diplomatic defeat for us for
india no it's not a diplomatic defeat
for india it is a reflection of india's
standing in the global power scenario
china is more powerful than india
it is a simple reflection of that the
day india becomes more powerful than
china the sri lankans will not dare to
do this
so please understand what diplomacy
actually is
diplomacy is war by other means and the
effectiveness of your diplomacy depends
on the size of your stick and how many
sticks you have
yeah so this is what what's going on
this is simply a reflection of ground
realities
so if
for uh for india to
not face the sort of situation in the
future india has to grow economically
and militarily it's not going to happen
next week
it's going to take 10 years minimum
so what i would suggest is get to work
all of you
contribute
in every single way you can
if you don't like what's happening you
don't like what's happening stop wasting
time get to work and contribute to
building yourself up and through that
building the nation up
that's all it is
okay next question is by saurabh
what was the history of the great ruler
pushimitra song
some people claim that he destroyed
buddhism in india even rumi latapa did
not support their claim that the
proclaimed that push
destroyed buddhist stupas etc all right
all right all right
who was pushyamitra sanga he
started a new dynasty after the downfall
of the mauryan dynasty the mauryan
empire
so pusha matrashonga was the general the
commander-in-chief
of the last mauryan king
[Music]
right
so
maurya was not a very good very able
very powerful king he was no longer
emperor he was no longer maharaja dhiraj
he was simply maharaja of magadha more
or less yeah his empire was crumbling he
was not able to
control
it very well he was not able to exercise
power very well and the nation was
suffering
the indian subcontinent which was
unified under
uh emperor chandragupta under emperor
ashok etc
was crumbling
there was a lack of political unity
everybody was being
various other members of the maury
dynasty were being opportunistic and
setting up their own kingdoms one in
gandha presenting afghanistan one
somewhere else one in kashmir and so on
yeah so that was what was happening
so this guy
the last king of the morius brian
was not a capable king he was not worthy
of being a king his general his
sinapathi commander-in-chief was pushia
matrashonga so what pushyamitra did was
during a military parade
in which he was demonstrating how
powerful the armies etc to his king
during this military parade he
assassinated with his own hands the king
and then
he became the king but he never called
himself maharaj he always called himself
for about 30 30 35 years i think 35
years in the second
century bce between 180 and 150 or so
bc
okay
now
he had to establish his legitimacy that
i am the right kind of guy to rule the
nation and what he did was he again
consolidated the empire the nation right
so he was able to expand his kingdom and
wage certain military campaigns and he
brought back some of the old glory that
had been lost over time because of the
uh because of the slow decline of the
mauryan dynasty
now he had different policies than what
the mauryans had for instance ashok is
the guy ashok is the emperor
who brought buddhism out of obscurity it
was just an obscure little sect and he
he catapulted buddhism to global
superpower status that's what ashok
morya did
then you had a king called samprathi
who was the last great mauryan emperor
he was the grandson of ashok he was the
son of ashok's blind son kunal
so samprathi
he was a great patron of jainism
it is said that he built more than 150
000 jain temples
uh all across the empire
then again various other kings came in
other descendants and they i believe
went back to patronizing buddhism now
when pushing
became the emperor of india
i believe he stopped
patronizing
buddhism so whatever privileges buddhism
was getting under the previous mauryan
kings all ended all disappeared but
there is zero evidence whatsoever that
there was actual persecution
of buddhism right so there is there are
some buddhist texts one of which is
called the ashoka vadana i believe in
which it is said that pushvitra was evil
and he persecuted the buddhists and
things like that that's what this
buddhist text claims but on the other
hand you have a sri lankan buddhist text
called the mahavanja
which mentions
which records that there were various
buddhist monasteries
present in flourishing in magadha itself
during the time that pusha mithra was
the king so the sri lankan
records
tell us a very different story than what
is portrayed in the mahavanja so this
looks like something that
the various buddhist leaders of the time
were not happy that they lost the great
privileges that they had otherwise
before bishop
came to power
and that's why they have portrayed him
as a cruel guy and as somebody who
uh
not destroyed but persecuted buddhism we
know
that during the the
shunga dynasty buddhism was alive and
well it was doing well right i think the
the uh
ashoka vadhana says that
killed some some
buddhist monks and priests and all that
it is even claimed that he went to
chagall which is present-day seaal court
in
temporarily in pakistan he went there
and he offered a bounty of 100 roman
dinaris
for the head of every buddhist monk that
was killed or something like that
the funny thing is that at that time
the roman dinars were not even prevalent
in india
yeah the the ashoka
was written much later
so that's the kind of thing it is it
looks like a battle of narrative battle
it looks like propaganda to make this
guy look bad because he did not support
buddhism to the extent that they wanted
and that's how it is so there is no
actual evidence whatsoever there is zero
evidence zero that position
persecuted buddhism and tried to
whatever destroy buddhism or whatever
right there is no evidence for this
whatsoever
laksha says you've said that ching is
khan was the greatest emperor of all
time have i
however i think that samrat vikramaditya
the great was far superior since he is
described as an incredibly fair and just
king who never did anyone harm his rule
is described as a golden era that
assured in unprecedented levels of peace
and prosperity
uh what do you think
okay
so let's talk about
emperor vikramaditya we have an entire
ila
named after emperor vikramaditya which
is the vikram samwat era
um so how do we compare let's say
vikramaditya with let's say ashok
when it comes to ashok there are
mentions of ashok in various
records historical records the sri
lankan records uh
extensively mentioned ashok they mention
his children sangamitra in mahinda who
came to sri lanka to propagate the
buddhism and brought the brought a
sapling of the bodhi tree with them yeah
sangamitra
and so on we also know that ashok had a
vast empire because of the various
pillars and edicts he placed at the
boundaries of his empire we know that it
encompassed
present-day afghanistan gandhar
western punjab and the other extent in
the east as well and we know how far it
it extended to the to the south as well
and there are inscriptions of ashok
which mentioned him as predator sri
pyradhi and so on so there is copious
abundant evidence
that ashok was the emperor of india and
we know reasonably when well when he was
the emperor of india when it comes to
vikramaditya
there is a lack of evidence there are no
inscriptions that
that are unmistakably referring to
emperor vikramaditya
there are no other texts that we know of
from other places maybe sri lanka maybe
from from rome maybe from greece maybe
from from
tibet or whatever that mentioned that
there was a king called vikramaditya in
india
there is a lack of evidence there is not
one piece of evidence that you can
consider to be unmistakable undeniable
incontrovertible now please understand
i've said this before let me say this
again
the absence of evidence is not evidence
of absence
i am pretty sure that emperor
vikramaditya was a real person he really
existed uh india's historians you know
uh post independence stories they say
that he is a mythical king i don't agree
with that i am quite sure that he
existed but i have no evidence
that he actually existed and i have no
evidence of how large or small his
empire would have been and therefore i
cannot pass any kind of judgment
on him
when i say that the
mahabharata actually happened it's
because we have evidence that it
actually happened events that are
described in the mahabharata are now
known to be true
the sinking of dwarka because of a
tectonic event we know it happened that
the city is there we found it we
discovered it under the ocean
yes off the coast of present-day the
dwarka so we know that exactly what is
written in the mahabharata exactly that
that same thing has happened and that's
why we can say with great confidence
that this event the events of the
mahabharata most likely not most likely
the hundred percent happened
similarly with the ramayana with the ram
sithu thing and all that it is still a
work in progress but we are reasonably
sure that the raman also
has historical basis right now when it
comes to emperor vikramaditya i
am pretty certain that he existed and
maybe he was a great great emperor but
we have no actual evidence of that and
therefore i cannot pass any judgment
that he was greater than this or greater
than that it's like that it's simple
logic this is the scientific method
this is how you examine things and and
analyze things based on evidence only
not based on feelings or emotions or
stories
yeah
so
i'm not sure what i've said about
ching's did i say he was the greatest
emperor i said i must have certainly
said that he was the greatest conqueror
that we know of in recorded history
um
so yeah i i i don't have any basis
for comparing
chingishan with emperor vikramaditya
some people say that his empire was all
over asia arabia was also part of that
okay you make the claim but can you
please substantiate that claim with some
actual evidence
i am yet to see any piece of evidence
i'm not saying that because there is no
evidence today it means it never
happened we may discover evidence in the
future our archaeologists and historians
have been sleeping the past 70-80 years
so once they wake up and start doing
work we may uncover evidence of the fact
that vikramaditya really ruled in india
but thus far we have none of that
some people even said that he defeated
the julius caesar and
from where do these stories come from
please if you make a claim show me the
evidence that corroborates your claim
that's just as simple as it is and
therefore i have to regrettably say i
have no basis for comparing
emperor vikramaditya with ching is khan
and therefore i cannot
make
any value judgment
yeah so i don't know what the stories
say i don't go by stories i i've heard
the stories but i need evidence for me
to actually say that this actually
happened i am
hopeful that we will discover the
evidence i am pretty certain that
emperor vikramaditya did exist and that
he was a great king we don't know how
great he was only when we find evidence
of the extent of his empire will we know
how great he actually was
that's all i can say about this
mother says uh thank you sir
why is it that bhagat singh is highly
revered in indian discourse but we never
heard hear about
hemu kalani who was hanged by the
british
by the brits at the young age of 19
yeah there are so many indian freedom
fighters who have also
done the supreme sacrifice they have
sacrificed their lives they sacrificed
their lives for the nation and no one
remembers them and some people get the
privilege of being worshipped everywhere
i am not saying that we should not uh
revere bhagat singh for what he did he
was a young man with a whole life in
front of him and he gave it up willingly
with a smile for the
for the sake of the nation
yes so we obviously
um
must treasure the memory
of bhagat singh it doesn't mean that we
should ignore everybody else there are
other people who did the same thing who
gave up their lives
so hemukhalani is somebody who lived in
sindh
and
he participated in the quit india
movement
that mr gandhi had started
so if my memory serves me right the quit
india movement began in 1942 it was a
complete failure
yeah but
so
uh
participated in that and he had
different ideas from the what mr gandhi
was preaching
what he did
is i think in the town of the city of
sucker
in sindh there was this railway track
and he and some of his friends or
companions
tried to uh
try to derail a train
by sabotaging the railway track right
by pulling out some rails or something
like that and they were caught and the
british were able to prevent the
derailment from happening
so i'm not sure if all of them were
caught but hemu kalani was caught he was
apprehended he was imprisoned then he
was tortured they wanted him to reveal
the names of his fellow conspirators so
to say the people who had uh
who had collaborated with him in this
project of derailing a train
and he refused to give up their names
and for that the british hanged him this
is completely arbitrary application of
justice
the guy tried to do something that they
did not like
but he did not succeed
and i'm sure there were written rules
there was a whole penal code that the
british had started in the 80 in the
1800s the indian penal code came into
force was it 1830 or 1860 somewhere
around there right so nearly 100 years
before this thing happened 1943 this
happened
and i'm sure that
there was no death penalty prescribed
for
attempting to do something like this
anyhow this was completely arbitrary
application of justice and law
and because mother uh because
because hemu refused to divulge the
names
of the people who collaborated with him
because of that the british hanged him i
think in 1943.
so he gave up his life i think the age
of like you say 19 i think yeah
for the sake of the nation and no i
think
i mean almost no one know remembers him
so that's my point there are so many
freedom fighters beyond bhagat singh
chandrasekhar and raj guru and various
other people that we remember there are
way more people there are
there are hundreds of thousands of
indians who are going to give up their
lives for the sake of their freedom of
their people's freedom of their nation's
freedom it's it's it's a shame it's a
tragedy that we don't remember the names
there should be a memorial somewhere
where all the information all the names
that we have
in our records should be kept on display
so that people can at least go and see
the names and you know at least
at least see the name that this was a
person who gave up his or her life
for us
right so that's how it is india
unfortunately as of today does not
really
uh
does not honor
those the the true patriots
and it's sad it's unfortunate
and i'm sure that uh even pakistan
would not be honoring or remembering
because of his religion
sindh is now in pakistan right currently
so yeah that's just how it is
unfortunate
says i wonder why all the air reports on
china and taiwan by the us australia and
japan reporters never mentioned the 1972
agreement
recognized by the us in china
and what it says is the u.s
recognizes the government of the
people's republic of china as the sole
legal government of china there is but
one china and taiwan is a part of china
i get that the agreement is not in our
favor now but doesn't that that doesn't
mean
it doesn't exist or we can just ignore
it that is at the very heart of the
conflict with china
so
uh
you seem to be uh arguing on behalf of
china or in favor of china
that uh the us and the west has
reneged on its commitment on the
agreement that it had signed this was
called the 1972 shanghai community i
think yeah
in which the americans said that yeah we
recognize the one china policy and china
as one nation and taiwan is part of
china and all that this was in 1972
during the u.s china though during the
kissinger
new uh nixon era when nixon was
president yeah
and uh yes so the shanghai communique
did say something to this effect and
what mr eddie corleone is saying that
why is america not honoring this
commitment yeah
i mean
the agreement may not be in someone's
favor but it doesn't mean it doesn't
exist
the u.s should still honor
this commitment on this agreement this
communique that it put out in 1972 and
it should recognize taiwan as part of
china
okay
the thing is this
no nation
is bound
duty-bound
to
abide by a treaty that is not in its
interest
no nation is is duty bound to do that
if let's say in the in the past you
signed a treaty
and today you realize that it's not
in in your favor it is it is harmful it
is detrimental to your national interest
then it is
perfectly right for that nation to walk
away from the treaty whether it signed
it or not doesn't matter shall i give
you some examples have you heard of the
jcpoa
the joint comprehensive plan of action
the iran nuclear deal that the americans
signed in 2015 it became effective in
2015. yes the americans signed the
agreement what happened
2018 the withdrawal withdrew from the
agreement they walked away from it from
a signed agreement
it's happened have you heard of the
sino-british joint declaration
1984 was it
the sino-british joint declaration so
hong kong was supposed to come back to
china in
1997 was it somewhere around there
so the chinese and the british signed
this joint declaration in 1984 i
remember it was supposed to be effective
for 50 years
and it enshrined the principles of the
of the
uh
one country two systems that principle
so hong kong will go back to china but
it will be one country two systems hong
kong will have a separate system it will
be a self-governing
autonomous region of sorts with a high
degree of autonomy except for defense
and foreign affairs
right
the chinese were they they signed this
this joint declaration they agreed to it
but then what happened in 2020 in 2021
they went back on it and even before
that in 2014 or 2015 the chinese said
that this agreement this this thing no
longer applies so the chinese
went back on the treaty that they had
they said unilaterally this no longer
applies so that's how it is
that's always how it is so you can't
have your cake and eat it too you can't
run with the hair and hunt with the
horns
you you are you are uh
arguing on in favor of china but you are
ignoring what the chinese themselves
have been doing
the chinese can never be trusted to keep
any agreement never ever ever ever
look at their past history of the past
60 70 years see the things they have
done
so please don't give me this
argument in favor of china that the
americans should abide by a signed
agreement or a communication the 72
shanghai community every nation has the
right to walk away from a treaty that is
detrimental to its national interest
that's just how it goes
treaty or not really doesn't matter
okay abdul bassett says what do you
think about the indian air force still
running still flying the aging mig-21s
and the hindustan aeronautics limited hl
facing difficulties in the production
rate of the tejas
um i think it is it is
deeply deeply unfortunate that uh the
indian air force is still operating the
mig-21s the mig-21s belong in museums
that plane that fighter plane was the
state-of-the-art most advanced fighter
plane i believe in the 1950s or 1960s
yeah
and it's it's totally obsolete but
the indian air force is still flying it
and i don't blame the indian air force
for this
it is the various
governments
in india that have totally delayed
the procurement
of of new fighter planes
uh there was this
about 20 or so years ago india was
supposed to acquire 114
fighter planes
and we're still waiting for that to
happen for some reason the defense
procurement process is incredibly slow
yeah
and that's why we are still flying these
ancient
museum peace aircraft it is it is really
really unfortunate in the future the
jaguar fighter planes will also become
will have to be phased out i think the
mig-21s will be phased out i believe by
20 25 26 somewhere around there and by
2030 or thereabouts even the jaguars and
possibly even the mirages
could be phased out because they are
also going to be going to be like you
know long in the tooth
so the solution right now is to really
ramp up the production rate of the pages
and to really get going on the
development of the amca the admin
advanced medium combat aircraft and
whatever else is coming maybe the twin
engine deck the deck based fighter and
various other things that are that are
in in progress
and possibly acquire more fighter planes
from abroad as a stop gap solution maybe
get 36 more rafales maybe a hundred more
of us whatever you know in the late 90s
mid 90s late 90s the french actually
offered the indian government of that
time
they
made this offer to india
they offered india
they offered to move the factory
that makes mirage 2000 aircraft to india
and they said that india can build as
many of the aircraft as it likes and the
indian government did not take up this
offer
india would have been the manufacturing
hub the manufacturing base of the mirage
2000 fighter fighter plane
the mirage 2000 fighter plane is one of
the aircraft that participated in the
bala could strike
across the border into pakistani
occupied the terrorist
territory right
it's a great aircraft india could have
had the manufacturing capability for the
mirage 2000 and india could have
manufactured 100 200 300 for its for its
own purpose for its own sake
the indian government of that time
whoever it was in power at the time they
did not
make this happen
and now we are in this situation
so i think
for the time being it makes sense for
india to acquire maybe a hundred or so
foreign aircraft
and it doesn't make sense to acquire a
new
make of aircraft maybe the f-16 f15 or
whatever else people may be talking
about india should acquire an aircraft
that it already has the rafale makes
sense
so acquire 36 more maybe 100 more 114
more whatever do that
in the meanwhile india needs to ramp up
the production rate of the pages i don't
know how many pages fighter planes are
being built per year right now is it 16
per year
uh you we could set up
another assembly line which produces 16
more per year i don't think that's a
very big problem
you just have to sign something
and uh
issue the budget for it so uh that is
something that can be solved reasonably
quickly in a couple of years yeah and
then we could be producing double the
number of pages that got per year
so yeah that is something that needs to
be done so i think it is really
unfortunate that we are still flying
these ancient museum pieces it is the
fault of various successive governments
over the past 20 or so years
they have uh allowed this problem to
fester and it's becoming
like really bad now yeah
so yeah that's that's what i can say
we need to have a quick stop-gap
solution uh
how many squadrons do does india need to
have
fighters fighter plane squadrons 43 is
it i think right now india has about 30
fighter plane squadrons out of which
many many of those are that of the
mig-21s
so their needs there is an urgent need
for india to acquire
new fighter planes and i hope that
something will be done soon about this
okay summat says will india import
bombers strategic bombers from russia
will the u.s take a risk and sanction in
india if this happens
is india economically ready for such
kinds of sanctions so i'm hearing these
days in the past week or so this this
report this rumor
that india is going to acquire only i
think six tupolev 160 strategic
bombers from russia
i'm not sure how true this is i'm not
sure if the army or the air force has
made the statement
it looks like
some high-ranking person made made some
remarks about this while delivering a
speech
but i'm not sure if this has been
confirmed or whether it's just a rumor
i am going to consider this to be a
rumor as of now but let's say so so i'm
not sure if it's really going to happen
if it's really happening then my
question is don't we have a much
bigger need
of investing that sort of money into
acquiring fighter planes
we only have
about 30 squadrons of fighter jets we
need 43 i believe 34 i don't know what
the number is we have a shortage
yeah we have a shortfall
of fighter planes and that is what we
need more than strategic bombers in my
opinion yeah so what would strategic
bombers be used for it obviously is not
aimed at pakistan pakistan is a narrow
country no strategic depth yeah and we
can use fighter planes to do the job
when it comes to
dealing with pakistan in in case it's
needed
strategic bombers so the tupolev 160
that is being talked about the white
swan aircraft uh let's see what it looks
like because why not
what does a tupolev
160 look like so that i can put that on
the screen and display it
um
one second let me share my screen
what does this aircraft look like
here's what it looks like it's a nice
looking aircraft
yeah that's what it looks like it is a
supersonic
strategic bomber
there it is flying over mountains and
snow and stuff
here it is again
so this is an aircraft that is a very
long range twelve thousand plus
kilometers
so if you if the aircraft takes off it
can go six thousand kilometers one way
and come back another six thousand
kilometers back to home base
twelve thousand kilometers overall range
more than that most likely more than
twelve thousand kilometers it can also
it also has the
in-flight refueling capability which can
extend its range significantly
and it can carry a enormous payload
40 45 tons 40 000 45 000 tons
of weaponry bombs missiles cruise
missiles whatever else yeah
uh
nuclear
weapons as well
so that's the kind of thing it is that's
the kind of aircraft it is so this is
the kind of and it's a super sonic
aircraft i think it is it is mach 2 plus
which means it can travel at more than
twice the speed of sound if i
if my memory serves me right
so it's a very good aircraft
uh
and the only
reason india would acquire something
like this
would be
with would be with china in mind
so uh
that's what i can think of now uh
it does make sense to have some aircraft
like these strategic aircraft
supersonic mach 2 kind of aircraft with
a massive payload capability and a
massively
large long range
so in case there is
a conflict with china we can go deep
into chinese territory at supersonic
speeds and this is this is an aircraft
that that can evade various defenses i'm
sure
and we could deliver certain payloads
deep into china or into the heart of
china if required using these aircraft
so it makes sense to have this but is it
is it a crying necessity right now is it
that urgent
is is the acquisition of fighter planes
more squadrons of fighter planes not a
more urgent thing especially when we
have mig-21s which we should not be
flying
so that's what that's
because of these questions it it kind of
makes me
think
that this report these reports we're
hearing may just be rumors i am not sure
it's been confirmed by the indian air
force so let's wait and watch if we are
doing it then there may be good reason
for it but it's not been confirmed yet
as far as i know yeah
yeah the other question is
will the americans sanction india if
india acquired the tupolev 160 bombers
oh for sure
so the americans have made a big
exception for india very nice
magnanimously and kindly
they have decided not to impose cat
sanctions on india for acquiring the s
400 missile defense system yeah how nice
of them i think that if india goes in
ahead and acquires the tupolev 160 then
in that case the americans will
definitely sanction india
so i'm not sure
if india wants to go ahead and do that
antagonize the americans but if it is
something that is good for india if our
defense planners strategists
think believe and have calculated that
this is what we need for right now then
india should go and do it and let the
americans do whatever they want to do
yeah and we can deal with the
fallout of that because even the
americans will face certain uh
well they will also face
certain consequences if they decide to
sanction india because they need india
as an ally of sorts at least in the quad
in the i2u2 dialogue thing and as a
counterweight to china
so yeah let's see how it goes but as far
as i know this is not yet confirmed
okay man vashishta says what would have
happened if lavrenti beria
would have become the soviet premier
after the death of joseph stalin
and why were there tensions between
gregory malenkov lavren tiberia and
nikita khrushchev after the death of
stalin
so this person lavrenti beria was the
head of the nkvd the secret service the
secret police or whatever
he was a very powerful man in the ussr
and
yeah this this is during the time of
joseph stalin it is alleged that when
stalin fell ill
it is alleged that lavrenti beria may
have
kind of
hastened
the demise of joseph stalin
it is alleged by joseph stalin's own
family
anyhow so uh
when did stalin die
60s
63 was it 53 i don't remember let me
just quickly take a look at when he died
stalin did when did he die
yes he died in 1953 so when joseph
stalin died
there was a power struggle
in the ussr
and uh
and who came after him
so yeah i i don't quite remember who
came after him though there was a gap
there was this in this period of weak
leadership before nikita khrushchev came
into power
uh stalin was the general secretary of
the thing
uh
so after stalin it was nikita khrushchev
anyhow so
so the question is what would have
happened if lavrenti berya had become
the soviet premier you see lavrenti
berya was a very nasty person joseph
stalin
did not trust
lavrenti berya he trusted him to carry
out his orders and do all the all the
dirty work for him
and all that cut out purges and
executions of
of of uh dissenters and whatnot yeah
but
on one occasion
stalin's daughter
was alone in her house and lavren
tiberia also happened to visit the house
stalin immediately called his daughter
on the phone and said get out
don't be alone with lavrinth area
so that's the kind of guy he was
he after lavrenti beria was executed i
believe in 1953 he was executed yeah
he was shot
in moscow
for
whatever reason yeah reasons don't
matter
so after beria died eventually it
emerged that he was a serial killer and
worse
if you can imagine something worse than
being a serial dealer yeah
and
in the 90s i believe there was this
there is this apocryphal story
yeah i don't know if it's true or not
but i read about it a long time ago
so there was this building there is this
building in moscow
that
in the 90s or whenever this happened it
served as the embassy of tunisia
tunisia is a north african country so
this building served as the embassy of
tunisia
now a new tunisian embassy ambassador
comes into this building and he is he
lives there with his wife
and his wife
is not comfortable there at night she
hears screams
and when she goes out in the into the
corridor she sees
a girl
running naked and then she disappears
that sort of thing
and this continued for some time and
then there was some plumbing work that
was that was going on
on the side of the building for that
they had to do some digging
and when they did the digging and they
opened up the the thing and all that
they discovered multiple skeletons of
women and girls that had been buried
there and the dating was done in it it
was dated to the time when lavrenti
beria was in occupation of that house
yeah
so uh
he was a serial killer and much worse
than that it is now known
so if somebody like that had become the
premiere of the soviet union sovereign
union the soviet union would have been i
believe much worse than
it would have been
bad for the people of the ussr and maybe
other people as well yeah
so that's uh about lavrenti beria why
were the tensions between three people
after the death of siren obviously
there's going to be a power struggle
the boss is dead there has to be a new
boss now in place and there will be two
three candidates who will all contend
for the big big seat for the big
position for the throne for the crown
and in this struggle lavrenti beria lost
out and he lost his life
and nikita khrushchev became the next
leader of the ussr so that's typical
of a transitionary period unless there
is a clear-cut transition that's already
pre-defined that was not the case there
was a power struggle and lavriti beria
was
shot
whoa that is a long question
sunbae says i'm i'm a manipuri mythical
i'm getting lots of questions from
manipur nice
i am really curious about the
introduction of hinduism and manipur
because i came to know recently that
through my mother that we had some other
religion where we had different gods
i know few of them now i have no clue
about it i'm a proud hindu girl
the question has been bugging me how and
when did hinduism come into manipur in
particular why krishna bhakti
heavily inspired by krishna
yeah classical dance form uh ras leela
chandan on the noses
i want to be a krishna bhakt but i'm
curious about this
when did hinduism come because before
that you had salamis
and so on so forth yeah okay the
question is what why when did hinduism
appear in manipur
and why vaishnavism why not shaivism and
so on right that's the question so
let's go to the map to understand this
better let me uh
once again bring in z map where is the
map
we were in israel the last time we were
at the map so we need to get out of
there
okay let's zoom out uh let me remove the
question from the screen where is
manipur manipur is right here in the
indian far east
yeah
between assam meghalaya and myanmar
burma yeah
so now we know this for a fact that the
entirety of southeast asia
was deeply hinduised for
for the past two thousand or so years
yeah
the thailand burma region was called
suvarnabhumi
you had various
hindu empires and kingdoms
in cambodia in vietnam in champadesh the
champa kingdom the champa empire
thailand was deeply hinduised indonesia
was hinduised you had indian culture all
across china all the way up to japan
even in in mongolia even in siberia and
so on and manipur is right here
and this has been going on for more than
2000 years way more than 2000 years so
hinduism would have always had some some
some kind of presence in manipur now
officially
hinduism comes
into manipur is the official so-called
state religion or whatever you want to
call it
uh
in the 17th century i believe during the
reign of king pameba
i think it's the 17th century if i'm not
if i if my memory serves me right
but there are temples
hindu temples in manipur that predate
this uh the the time of king pameba
so i believe hinduism would always have
had some presence in manipur manipur is
not some island isolated from the rest
of the world it's very much part of this
larger region
geographically
the indian far east is actually part of
southeast asia geographically
but culturally it's all part of the indo
sphere very much so
so uh
i would
i would say that why have the
esteemed professors at the university of
manipur not answered this question and
not brought out the facts
about exactly when money when hinduism
came into manipur so before hinduism we
had what the what the west calls sanama
ism
right surname is about the the the god
salam he and in the entire uh it's a
polytheistic obviously uh culture
there is ancestor worship this nature
worship there are various divinities
like sannamahi
laithana pakhanba and what not yeah
it's a polytheistic uh
culture and in it's it's very similar in
a whole lot of ways to hinduism there
are well you could consider pakhang but
to be just like lord shiva in in some
ways yeah
and the worship rituals are very similar
and so on so forth
so uh i believe that manipur would have
always had some presence
of hinduism in the past 2000 years uh
the history of manipur is very ancient
minimum 2000 years old most likely more
than three and a half thousand years old
uh
but it officially became uh
hinduism became the official state
religion of sorts
around the 17th century or so
now what was the other question yeah why
not shaivism
why was it only vaishnavism why not
shaivism
um
yeah that that reminds me there were
these saints in tamil nadu
they were called the alvars
so they lived in tamil nadu between the
fifth in the 10th century a.d somewhere
around there these were vaishnavite
saints they worshipped lord vishnu and
somehow there is some kind of relation
to terrorism connection between the
alvars and and manipur so
there was a significant influence of the
alwa and the bhakti movement in manipur
probably
possibly when the alvars were still
extinct in tamil nadu or maybe just
after that
so that is way before king pamahima was
even born
yeah so that is the old version of
influence in manipur now in tamil nadu
there were the nayanars also
these were also tamil saints these were
shiva bhakts they were shaivite saints
so that's also around the same time
more or less as the alvars but somehow
the mayonnaise did not influence manipur
the alvarez did
and later on because of the proximity
between manipur and the gowdadesh
bengal
you had the influx of bengali ideas into
manipur because of the close proximity
geographical proximity so you had the
influx of gaudiya vaishnavism ideas into
manipur
you had this
chaitanya mahaprabhu is a very
influential figure and then you had this
person called shantidas gosai who
actually convinced it is alleged that he
convinced king king pamiba to
uh
officially make uh gaudiya vaishnavism
the state religion or whatever they call
it of manipur
yeah so that's what it is there are
various parts of india where you have
vaishnavism and shaivism at the same
time for instance if you go to the
other end of india the extreme west
currently the extreme west of india is
gujarat
right
so in saurashtra let's say you have
dwarka which is where lord krishna ruled
for a period of time
and there are lots of people in this
region who are who worship lord krishna
who are very fond of lord krishna you
also have right next door to dwarka the
great jyotirling of sumnath very ancient
temple it is said lord krishna himself
visited subnath
when he was king in dwarka very ancient
so you have people who worship
lord shiva as well so that's how it is
it's always been that sort of culture
india lots of different uh paths
available to people you go and choose
what you want so in manipur you had what
is called sanama everything is an ism
yeah it is a polytheistic system with
ancestor worship spirit worship nature
worship and so on
and that
syncretize itself beautifully with
hinduism with with gaudiya vaishnavism
similar to how shinto
the original japanese polytheistic
belief system
syncretize itself beautifully with
hinduism and buddhism yeah very similar
so that's what it is
and we don't know exactly when hinduism
first appeared would have been maybe
2000 years ago maybe before that
but according to the great historians it
all begins with uh lord
palmeira
but obviously that is not quite the case
i am sure there are temples
in manipur
that predate
the king uh pamela
there is this uh
hanuman temple in imphal which may be
older yeah so
if you just scratch a little bit below
the surface you will find more data and
my question is why do the great
professors and historians in the history
department of manipur university
why don't they
provide answers to these questions
it's disappointing disappointing
i don't like being disappointed
okay saurabh says is it true that r1a1
that lineage the genetic lineage
was found worth is found in higher
frequencies in tribal peoples of madhya
pradesh and andhra pradesh respectively
so what is r1a1 it is an ancient genetic
lineage it's a petri lineal lineage
passed down from father to son father to
son father doesn't follow to some
petroleum lineage it is
about 25 26 27 28 000 years old
so what is a haplogroup it's a
haplogroup right r1 even r1a r1a
whatever or r1 it's a haplogroup what is
a haplogroup a haplogroup is an extended
family
it's it's a group of people in extended
family all of whom
have a certain genetic mutation that
originates
in one single individual
at a
time in the past
so the r1a1 or r1a haplogroup
is an extended family of males
who have a certain genetic mutation that
originated in one
single man about 27 28 000 years before
today
most likely
that man
the originator of this extended family
lived in india about 27 26 to 28 000
years before today
so it is an extended family that
whose numbers are incredible
more than one billion men today have
this particular genetic mutation
that began in india
all this time ago right
and
it is found in great concentrations in
high frequencies in india in the indian
subcontinent
and in eastern europe uh let's let's try
to take a look at uh the distribution
right
r1a1
distribution
let us see what it looks like if i can
share it on the screen
go to google search for that and then
put on images
there we are
so as you can see this is the
distribution the the pink or the purple
areas are the other places where you
have high frequencies high
concentrations of individuals who carry
this mutation
so as you can see it is centered around
the indian subcontinent there is a part
there is a
region
in
the tarin basin area
and then there is eastern europe poland
germany the slavic parts of
europe russia etc so these are the
places where you have men
who are descended from
this ancient indian person
and it has this this haplogroup has been
linked
to the spread of indo-european languages
across eurasia the so-called aryan
invasion so there are these various
journalists
yeah who have portrayed r1a1 as the
aryan gene it's not a gene it's a
mutation geniuses
please learn that anyway so they call it
the rn gene
and they said that it will be found in
high frequencies in brahmins and blah
blah blah blah blah blah it came from
central asia apparently with white
aryans
who brought in this evil hinduism and
evil sanskrit language into india and
displaced the dravidians and then
the high caste people so-called
high-cast people carry the rng
and the tribals and the dravidians
unfortunately don't unfortunately don't
have it now what is the truth you asked
a good question
let me search for that
okay let me share
let me share this
uh give me a second to put it on the
screen
there is this research paper that i
would like to bring to your attention
your kind attention
this is from 2009 the indian origin of
the paternal haplogroup r1a1 star
substantiates the author's origin of
brahmans in the caste system and so on
now let's take a look at do you talk
about andhra pradesh and all that right
so uh there are two tribes that it
mentions here it's in the conclusions
part of the research paper
the co-presence of this haplogroup in
many of the tribal populations of india
its existence in high frequency in
sahara
the saharya
tribe is from madhya pradesh i believe
and the chenchu tribe is from
andhra pradesh yeah
and so on so it says there are higher
frequencies in these
tribes so in the chenchu tribe of andhra
pradesh
27 almost of the people
carry this
mutation they are part of this extended
family and when it comes to the sahara
tribe of madhya pradesh central india
this
genetic mutation is found
in
approximately 26 to 27 percent of the
males who were studied
so these are tribal groups tribal
populations they are supposed to be the
victims of the rn invasion not the
aryans themselves right
and yet you find this now let's take a
look at something more
so this table
shows us
uh
the age of this mutation in various
ethnic groups or various groups in india
and other parts of the world also europe
pakistan and so on so in india
um what we find is that the average age
of this haplogroup is between 12 800
years and 28 almost 29 000 years
the average over here it says is 23 652
years
when it comes to the sahara tribe the
average age is almost 28 000 years
which means the oldest
examples of this mutation are in the
sahara tribe in these tribal populations
not in the so-called brahmins or
kashmiri pandits or whatever
where is kashmiri pundits it's only 24
000 years in the kashmir pundits in
indian brahmins it's fifteen thousand
seven hundred something years
maharashtra brahman's twelve thousand
years gujarat brahmins blah blah
fourteen thousand fourteen thousand
twelve thousand seventeen thousand
but in the tribal groups it's older
isn't that incredibly strange and and it
totally flies in the face of everything
these historians and journalists
business journalists etc are claiming
this mutation the r1a mutation is
supposed to have come in through the
aryan invasion which came from europe
and central asia so how come tribal
populations have way older
examples of this
of this mutation
you see all these lies are now crumbling
like a pack of cards anyhow so what
you're saying is right
they have these this haplogroup is found
in high frequencies
in
various tribal peoples in andhra pradesh
madhya pradesh et cetera in higher
frequencies than other other populations
other other ethnic groups or whatever
you want to call it
okay descendant of
rigvedic clans asks
how did the people of the saraswati
hindu region civilization whatever look
like what was their appearance like
why in cyprus anatolia central asia and
iran zebu cattle figurines are found
and even european cattle have zebu
cattle ancestry is there any connection
with out of india theory
so when it comes to uh
what did the people
from that period of our history look
like the saraswati sindhu era uh i don't
think there anybody has done a proper
professional
craniofacial reconstruction let me just
try and see
let me see if anybody has done it
um um
yeah let me show you what what they've
done these uh
there was something done recently but
it's very disappointing very very
disappointing i mean take a look at this
they found two skeletons
and they did this sort of reconstruction
of their faces you can't even tell if
it's male or female it's so poor and so
shoddy and so unprofessional
so yeah we have lots of examples of
skulls and skeletons from this era and
yet nobody
has bothered
to do this yeah
what is this typical this is something
else it's not from that era from from
our civilization
so yeah this may be an example but i'm
not sure how reliable this is
so maybe this isn't
oh i see it's your display picture
okay okay so yeah this could be
something like that
see
the people of that phase of our
civilization would have looked like
indians of today more or less
that's what i would imagine until they
actually do this and do it properly we
don't know but i would say they would
have looked like just all other indians
okay
that's what i can say now the other
question is quite interesting about zebu
cattle so when you go to cyprus anatolia
central asia iran
etc you find this figurines carving
statuets of zebu cattles ribocattle
even in in europe
why is that so so once again let's uh
look it up
zebu cattle
how did zebo cattle spread
is the question isn't it where did they
come from look
zebu cattle originate in india there is
absolutely no question about it there is
no ambiguity about the fact that the
zebu cattle
originate in india
uh
it's called boss indicus now this is a
paper about the spread of zebu cattle
from south asia they call it from the
indian subcontinent to the eastern
mediterranean region and it's a marker
of indo-european population dispersal so
all these zebu cattle they initially
originated from india and then they are
now they are found in
in africa
they entered africa at least four
thousand years before today
they found all across the middle east
iran is actually physically part of the
indian subcontinent sub continent it's
right next door to balochistan and since
so it's not a big surprise that you find
zebu cattle uh evidence of that over
there but anatolia is further west and
europe is for the west
now cattle
don't go for a walk
cattle are domestic animals cattle don't
decide one day okay let's go let's go
and migrate 5000 kilometers westward or
eastward cattle don't do that
cattle go wherever their masters take
them
the migration routes of cattle are
essentially the migration routes of
human beings
so if you find cattle in in some place
in europe it means that somebody took
those cattle to europe
uh so
the fact that we find
ancient indian cattle
in egypt
around 2000 bc indicates that indians
took those cattle to egypt
you find indian cattle in anatolia
it indicates that indian indians human
beings took those cattle there we find
that these cattle then mated with the
local cattle and produced new breeds
there are a variety of indian cattle
derived breeds in africa there are a
variety of indian cattle derived breeds
in the middle east in europe etc
and when they did the genetic analysis
of this which uh like you can see in
this paper this is one example of many
what was found is that in these mixed
breeds the patrilineal lineages were
those of indian cattle and the
matrilineal lineages were those of the
other the cattle from the various places
they were found
which means that the indians who
migrated to these places took male oxen
wolves with them
and had those bulls interbreed with the
local cattle to produce new breeds so it
was done deliberately and systematically
now let's see what this paper concludes
so you mentioned all those
examples of figurines and all that here
we are
lots of different examples
uh
is
turkmenistan i believe
it's close to the indian
to the indian subcontinent and so on and
so forth but what are the conclusions of
this paper let's find out conclusion the
spread of zebu cattle from the indus
valley to the east mediterranean region
including syria anatolia cyprus
palestine correlates well with the
present geographical distribution of
human y chromosome haplogroups lm11
r2 and r1az93
originating from hindustan and end of
south asian human genome k5
and the south indian human genome k16
so these sets of data correlate with
maps showing the relative proportions of
zebu admixture
and so on and so forth
these human populations and domestic
hump cattle movements are to be
connected with the dispersal of
indo-european languages
spoken
indo-aryan and iranian and extinct
casside in methane
anatolian from hindustan to asia minor
between 7000 bc and 1000 bc this paper
is explicitly saying that indo-european
languages spread out of india westwards
and the presence of hebrew cattle in
these regions is testament to that
this is an explicit
and very clear unambiguous statement of
that fact
right
it's connected with the dispersal of
indo-european languages
from hindustan to asia minor which is
the middle east and the in the anatolia
region around 7000 bc and and
further onwards from there
there you have it out of india theory so
like this this person asks
it is indeed connected to the out of
india theory which is a fact it is
indeed a fact it's not a theory it's a
fact
okay
what is your opinion about russia
purchasing iranian drones i'm in iranian
asking haha
so i'd say it's it's good for russia and
good for iran as well so uh the
ukrainians are deploying a turkish drone
bhairakthar drone which is a medium
altitude long endurance drone
it's used for
you know doing either reconnaissance
missions or
or even doing missile strikes on various
targets yeah
now we know that there was a war between
the armenians and the azerbaijanis in
2020 the nagorno-karabakh war
in which the azerbaijanis they used
israeli drones harop drones these are
loitering munitions they loiter for a
long time and then they go and
destroy the target they use these harop
drones in large numbers these loitering
munitions these are essentially suicide
drones kamikaze drones they loiter for
for hours possibly and then without
warning they will go and strike the
target so the drone itself will go and
strike the target it will not shoot a
missile the target it it itself is a
missile
so the azerbaija azerbaijanis use these
drones in massive numbers numbers and
that contributed to the victory over the
uh
armenians yeah
um
so that is a great lesson for 21st
century warfare that the mass use of
loitering munitions is key to military
success in a lot of scenarios now the
iranians have been
working on drone technology for a very
long time they acquired i believe
um
a lockheed martin drone that crashed on
iranian territory i believe and they
were able to retrieve it in reasonably
good condition and then they reversed
engineered it
it was a lockheed martin
martin
flying wing kind of drone
and they they reverse engineered and
they've produced their own drone called
the shahid 191 or something
and they've also produced
their version of the mq-1 predator drone
of the americans they call it the head
something else yeah
so they have these draws these work
reasonably well uh
and the prices are low they are
reasonably affordable
and maybe the russians
feel that it's it's a worthwhile
investment to acquire a large number of
affordable and reasonably good quality
drones yeah
so uh
that's what i've heard the americans
have publicized the fact that the
russians are buying these drones the
russians i don't think have made any
statements but yeah in case they're
buying it good for them what does it
indicate
i'm not sure if the russians produce
drones
but maybe they feel the need to have
some drones
and maybe that's why they want to
acquire them and test them out and see
how it works and maybe use them to uh
to go ahead in their ukraine campaign so
yeah so overall good for russia good for
iran yeah
okay couple more questions maybe
anime says what changes
will we start seeing as a nation
upon become becoming an economic
superpower will there be better
infrastructure better medical support
systems cultural upliftment
less low level corruption in the nation
or will the change be primarily
strengthening india's geopolitical
population position
see
these changes that you are specifying
mentioning better infrastructure better
medical systems
cultural
upliftment
less corruption
these changes
are not the outcome
of becoming a massive economy
these changes are the necessary
conditions
for becoming
an economic superpower
so it is not the outcome of becoming
an economic superpower but on the other
hand
conversely becoming an economic
superpower is the outcome of doing these
things of
making better infrastructure
of
of waging war on corruption and all the
other things
it's the other way around you have to
first do these things
only then later can you become
an economic
superpower that's how it is
it's the other way around
so you can never become a superpower
economically without first addressing
these issues of infrastructure of
corruption of corrupt
bureaucrats of corrupt politicians of
corrupt institutions
and the various things you have to deal
with those problems first if you address
those problems and fix them then you are
very much on your way especially in a
nation like india to becoming a major
top three economy yeah
samartha says why
do so many different different virus
outbreaks come up in china for example
the recent lungya virus outbreak which
is happening right now
are these outbreaks some sort of
biological weapon tests because the
cases after a few days are null who 2
doesn't intervene for some reason what's
your opinion on this matter
um
i'm not sure if it's a biological weapon
test or whatever
china has had a long-standing history
of of gifting the world various viruses
there was this 1918 pandemic
the spanish flu pandemic that was first
discovered by the americans in spain the
americans first encountered this
influenza
outbreak in spain so they called it the
spanish flow this actually originated in
china yes
and the various plague epidemics that
ravaged europe in the middle ages in the
first millennium and the second
millennium most of these also originated
in china
yeah
and somehow they completely bypassed
india what is the reason anyhow that's
not that's not the question so china has
always been an incubator
of various epidemics and pandemics
whether it is bacterial
or or viral right
and what are the reasons for this
well the chinese have this
well this fascinating cultural trait
the chinese will eat everything that
moves
everything is fair game for them they
eat dogs i mean i'm not trying to
criticize them or demean them demean
them this is simply a dispassionate
observation
they eat almost every animal that they
can get their hands on whether it is
dogs whether it is cats
whether it is frogs whether it is um
centipedes
scorpions
um bats whatever right and
and and if you're a consumer of these
animals then you would have you have to
go to the market to get the animal
snakes
porcupines what not yeah
so you have to go to the market to buy
the animal and the meat right
and in these markets which are called
wet markets all these different animals
of various different species whether
it's animals or reptiles or birds or
whatnot they are kept in close proximity
in cages together so you will have a
cage
with let's say
bats on top of that there will be cage
full of snakes on top of that there will
be a cage full of uh
i don't know some other animal
porcupines or whatever
next to that there will be a cage full
of dogs so all these different animals
very different species that would never
intermingle in nature they are
placed
in close proximity in close contact with
each other now all of these animals
they are hosts to certain kinds of
pathogens
certain kinds of bacteria certain kinds
of viruses
and if you bring them together
unnaturally in this close contact with
each other there can be instances when
the viruses can jump from one species to
another and then you will have weird
mutations happening
and new viruses emerge out of that
so typically it is these wet markets
that are the incubators of new
kinds of viruses
and
so yeah so that's one of the reasons why
you have so many viral and other
outbreaks coming out of china
but one can of course never discount the
possibility of
some some other kind of foul play
uh being at work over here that's always
a possibility the chinese we know they
they are very interested in various
kinds of viruses whenever there's an
ebola uh epidemic in africa that the
chinese send some scientists there for
doing humanitarian work but they also
bring back samples of the virus don't
they
and so on they have these virology labs
which have dubious sponsors
far away from china
it's now been revealed so there's a
whole lot going on so you can never
discount
the possibility
of
something more than catches the eye
something more than meets the eye but
historically china has been an incubator
of various kinds of new pathogens
because of these practices that are
prevalent in china
karthik says why has the u.s not
produced a single female president till
today well the u.s is the oldest
democracy but haha no female president
of course
you may now have any time
a female president possibly
it could happen any time
i'm just i'm just guessing it could
happen
uh and the lady in question is not just
female
she's also black she's also white she's
also indian so the most diverse
president of all time could be on the
cards
possibly soon but the question obviously
is about the historical precedent why
has there never been a female president
it's because of american culture the
cultural norms the morse
the
the anglo-saxon culture the puritanical
roots of american society
so
it's
extremely uh
how do i put it
it's extremely puritanical the puritans
a were
group
in england
and
what happened is that
when king henry viii
was the king of england he broke off
from the catholic church because the
pope refused to allow henry viii to
divorce his wife queen catherine of
aragon who was spanish
henry viii was in love with this young
lady called anne boleyn
he wanted to marry her by divorcing his
pre-existing wife and for that he needed
the ascent of the pope
who was in rome and the pope refused to
do that so henry became really upset he
became really deeply miffed and he broke
off contacts he broke off ties with the
catholic church he set up his own church
in england the anglican church
he he adopted to some extent the the
the teachings the the
the values of martin luther and that's
how england became a protestant
nation yes
now these these people the puritans
puritans they were not quite
happy
with the
extent to which religion had been
reformed in england they wanted even
more reforms
they were deeply dissatisfied that you
have not reformed christianity far
enough we need more we need more
and many of these puritans they crossed
the atlantic and eventually settled in
the americas in north america
uh in the massachusetts etc rhode island
around that region that that area
would you like to see it on the map
why not because we have a map here we
should see
let me put it on
where is the great map
of the world
so we're talking about the
puritans who were in england from there
they crossed the atlantic
and they ended up in the northeast
of the united present-day northeast of
the united states right
maine massachusetts this overall region
i don't know the specifics of where it
was yeah and then then they continued
their cultural practices their purity
puritan practices of of being hyper
rigid and religious
and
one of their cultural traits was that
women
must be subordinate to men
women must obey their husbands
and assume
a subordinate position in society
and uh one of the most unfortunate
events that happened in in north america
was the salem witch trials which were
instigated by puritans in which uh a
number of women were accused of being
witches and of communic with the devil
and many of them were
burned at the stake or hanged or
something
terrible terrible
ghastly event
so it was the puritans who
who instigated this who were the spark
for this and and
this is the foundation so to say
to a certain degree of american society
anglo-saxon anglo-saxon values pure
puritanical values right and women
historically have been
subordinate
citizens when the u.s constitution was
ratified women were not allowed to vote
it's it's a long-standing history
and feminism emerged as a justifiable
reaction to this it was needed
afterwards we know what happened to
feminism it got hijacked and now it's
not what it was supposed to be earlier
right but it emerged
as a cry of help for women who were so
badly oppressed in the us
and now we have the vocal movement
which which takes things to the other
extent which which places women on a
higher pedestal and than men and sees
men as the enemy so for the longest time
the united states has been
a deeply misogynistic nation women
if anybody from the us is watching
ask your mothers and your grandmothers
what kind of lives they lived and you
will know what i'm talking about it's
always been that way
and to cover up
this dark sordid history
the americans are now turning in the
opposite direction they are going all
work
in order it's to ensure that nobody
points fingers at them and shows in the
mirror that this is what you you've been
doing all this time because the
americans have a habit of lecturing the
world as to how the rest of the world
should live their lives
and and that's why they are doing this
so that nobody points finger at them
that's why they are going all woke and
all pro women and all anti-men now so
now men have dif very difficult lives in
the us
how the pendulum has swung so that in
short in brief is why the u.s has never
produced a single female president until
today
kuldip says
uh
one question my cousin's daughter asked
we always see in your sessions we see
maps yes
so the ten-year-old daughter asked if
the earth is around why is the west the
west in the east is the east
it's relative right yeah see
east west we can give it any name we
want
in sanskrit we call it poor in the
pastim i believe and you can call the
west the east and the east west but you
can call it whatever you want it's just
relative but how do we determine what is
east and what is west that's the
question
so unfortunately nowadays we don't go
out into the open we don't see the sky
we don't see the sun
so do this tomorrow morning ask your
niece
your cousin's cousin's daughter tomorrow
morning or whenever you meet her that
the next morning
when the sun is rising go outside the
house
and face the sun
don't look at the sun it's not good for
the eyes but face the sun feel the
sunlight on your face then put out your
right hand in one direction put out your
left hand in the other direction
right
so what you're facing
is
the east
the sun rises in the east
you're facing the sun you're facing the
east your left hand outstretched in this
direction
is the north
your right hand
is the south
and your
back is facing towards the west
so that's how you orient yourself if you
have the advantage of being able to see
the sun in the morning sunrise yeah
so yeah apart from that it's all
relative and there's also the concept of
the
the the fact that we have a magnetic
set of poles as well but that's a whole
different story
okay let's take one more question neil
says is it necessary to be a
non-vegetarian to excel in strength
sports
i read recently that roman gladiators
had pure vegetarian diets and their only
job was to fight what's your take on
this
okay let me give you an example instead
of telling you a story let me give an
example
um
vegan
strong man what was his name
let me put that on the screen so
germany's strongest man
is vegan
here we are what is his name his name is
patrick patrik
[Music]
he is of a persian origin he is of
iranian origin
and he is the strongest man he was the
strongest man in germany
yeah
and he was a vegan vegetarian vegan i
think he was vegan yes
so as you can see it is perfectly
possible to to acquire massive physical
strength
while
uh eating a plant-based diet so yes it
is not necessary to eat
meat in order to excel at strength
sports
you can do that if you eat the right
kind of vegetarian diet or vegan diet if
you prefer i think veganism is taking it
too far
you can include dairy products if you so
wish and eat a vegetarian diet
so you need
a good amount of protein and
to tell the truth
vegetarians have much a much wider range
of options when it comes to consuming
proteins
uh non-vegetarians they can only eat two
or three different kinds of meat and
that's all it is it's it's they complain
about it all the time chicken meat and
whatever else they eat in in case of the
vegetarians they can eat so many
different kinds of legumes
chickpeas
uh
kidney beans
various uh
other things yeah so there's a whole lot
of other options and it's actually
tastier so as long as you get the right
amount of protein and other nutrients
you're good
and when it comes to roman gladiators
they actually were slaves they were not
free so they were told what to eat but
yes
they discovered a cemetery a
burial place of gladiators and they did
tests on the bones and all that and they
were able to determine that their diet
was mainly
vegetarian
so yeah that was indeed the case
okay we are at the end of all the
questions now let me take
some questions for a couple of minutes
from the live chat
cows are forcibly made pregnant so that
they produce more will milk veganism is
all about human animal animal rights you
see in ancient india the population was
not this much
during the peak
during the
during the time when the so-called indus
valley civilization was as its peak the
greatest extent when it was fully
urbanized fully developed the most
high-tech uh high-tech civilization at
that time anywhere in the world
at that time the population of the
subtercino region extended region was
not more than 5 or 6 million human
beings
yeah
today it is 1.3 or 1.4 billion humans if
everybody drinks milk just imagine how
many liters of milk you need to produce
per day and that's why unfortunately
cows
are
facing this sort of exploitation when
you had far fewer human beings there was
no exploitation
cows were a form of currency cows were
incredibly valuable
so when you had a very small population
in this vast geographical area there was
no such exploitation and cruelty on
animals
veganism is all about animal rights and
yeah okay fine if you if you
you you can
live any lifestyle you wish and you're
absolutely justified in doing that it's
up to you
all right
um one or two more questions maybe
uh okay let us see what we have
eight billion people on the earth yes
there is that is indeed the case
says is it true that the us may offer
the f-35 aircraft to india with indian
specifications in the
mmrca multi
something role combat aircraft program
they may want to do it
but they will have all kinds of
conditions
india will have to sign all kinds of
agreements that will essentially uh open
up
india's
military secrets to the americans the
the spectrum the bandwidth and various
other compatibilities have to be met
first of all and secondly these aircraft
are incredibly expensive
yeah
you can buy
four or five pages fighters for the sake
of for the for the price of just one
f-35 or maybe more
incredibly expensive i'm not even sure
if they're that good yeah they have
stealth capabilities and all that but
yeah well
even if they offer it i don't think it's
worthwhile for india to take it
seriously and actually acquire these
planes
first of all we will have to hand over a
lot of our
um you know sign agreements that may not
be in our national interest so they may
offer it for sure
they would be happy if india were to buy
this but i don't think
it's in our national interest to acquire
these aircraft we should
make our own fifth generation fighter
planes the amca that's what it is
all right what else do we have
miguel diaz is i'm 19 is it too late for
me to become a mma fighter
it depends on the physical condition if
you're really fit you may still be able
to become one typically you have to
start training it at a slightly younger
age maybe 16 17 you know but i am sure
even if it even if you're 19 you may be
able to in a couple of years reach that
physical condition that's required of
mma fighters it's so you need to be
really really physically fit and strong
and flexible and you need to learn know
how to
fight and defend yourself and all that
you need to
learn a whole mixed bag of martial arts
techniques
boxing kicking punching kickboxing white
thai jiu-jitsu
and so on
it's it's uh
very tough but i'm sure it's possible if
you are truly dedicated and if that's
something you really wish to pursue
it depends on what kind of physical
condition you are in right now
all right what else do we have
all right what do we do what else do we
have
uh from the u.s how important is the u.s
work visa of the indian economy not that
much i mean india does get some
remittances some money flowing in
from the u.s people who go there on work
visas or h-1b visas or whatever other
visas are available
and they would typically send some money
back to india but i'm not sure if it's
that that much of a big deal you know
lots of indians want to do that they
want to go to the u.s immigrate their
own h-1b visas and eventually hopefully
many of them hope that they will
eventually acquire a green card and then
citizenship
i'm not sure if it really helps the
indian economy to a significant extent
so um
these remittances from other countries
from from from western nations they do
contribute a certain amount certain
percentage
to the indian economy i don't think it's
a whole lot and i don't think the indian
economy needs to depend on that or
should
should focus on that and stress on that
as a big component indian economy the
indian economy needs to grow in in its
own
way
through manufacturing and
such things yeah so i don't think it's
that significant or important in the
overall big picture context of the
indian economy
okay that brings us to the end of
today's session
uh yeah so thank you very much for all
your questions and we will
meet again in the next episode until
then take care have a good day good
night wherever you are and have a great
next week and happy independence day in
advance
all right thank you
take care bye